<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joel&#39;s Journal</title>
    <description>My personal place to write about the things I find interesting. Programming, Lisp, Ruby, Emacs, etc.</description>
    <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://joelmccracken.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>A Mid-Course Review of &quot;From NAND to Tetris&quot; on Coursera</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve been taking the course &quot;From NAND to Tetris&quot; on Coursera. So far,
the course has been very interesting, and I recommend it. It provides
a good taste of how computers work from a low level, starting at the
most basic logic gates and building up from there. I&#39;m over half way
through, and have some observations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This course has been a blast! Slowly building up a computer from
first principles has been very rewarding. Its an amazing
feeling to struggle with designing a chip and then to turn around
and use it in another, more advanced chip!
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The course hasn&#39;t been that hard. Now, I had some classes that
dealt with this kind of thing at Pitt. I remember working with
most of these concepts in the past, so this is not totally foreign
to me. However, I also think that the professors did an excellent
job simplify things to their essential concepts.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m really glad I have invested my time into this course. If you want
to learn more about how computers work on a low level (or even if you
would like a refresher into the topic), I highly recommend it.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/a-mid-course-review-of-from-nand-to-tetris/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/a-mid-course-review-of-from-nand-to-tetris/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scope Creep, or, the Decline and Fall of My Personal Projects</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
Scope creep can kill any project. There&#39;s no doubt about
that. However, it surprises me just how often this problem
manifests itself in my personal projects &amp;#x2013; that is, whatever I am
hacking on at the moment. I wonder what causes the
problem?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is easy to give in to the urge to slowly add more features to
projects. Its so easy to say &quot;Oh! one more thing!&quot;, especially when you
are your own boss, and there isn&#39;t necessarily anything that &lt;i&gt;needs&lt;/i&gt;
to be delivered &amp;#x2013; There isn&#39;t necessarily an end goal, or singular,
driving purpose. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You&#39;d think it would be easier to have a fixed scope on my own
projects. After all, I am the one who defines the scope. I&#39;m also
familiar with the problems of scope creep. As a general principle,
I think it is probably true that its easier to control the scope on
something you define (because &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; control and define it, after
all). However, I let my 
wandering curiosity influence the direction of the projects I work on.
This creates an ever-shifting set of goals that leaves a wake of
half-done things behind. This makes sense, because my satisfying my
curiosity brings me great pleasure &amp;amp; makes up a huge part of who I am.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem, though, is
that the spark of understanding comes, not at the &lt;i&gt;end&lt;/i&gt; of a project or
investigation, but at the beginning of the project when things are
still in a formative state. But once that understanding comes, it
&lt;i&gt;moves&lt;/i&gt;, ever forward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another aspect to this is that most of my personal projects do not
have an explicit goal I&#39;m trying to achieve. I start with &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; idea of what
I want to do, but the project is defined ad hoc as I work through
it. This is &lt;i&gt;fun&lt;/i&gt;, but I think it is less effective than having a
specific, finite goal in mind (at least effective for producing useful
artifacts). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m going to go one step further. There&#39;s another pattern I&#39;ve
noticed, and this one is a bit less self-indulgent: when something
gets too confusing and I get frustrated, I tend to drop the
project. I&#39;m probably less worried about this, because normally I
change gears and work on something that would fill in my knowledge
gaps, hopefully removing those frustrations. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess it ultimately depends upon what I&#39;m trying to do. Am I trying
to produce things on topics I love, or am I just trying to learn? If
I&#39;m trying to learn, is this the best way to do it? Am I just fooling
myself, getting exciting about projects and then dropping them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#x2014;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I recently started working on SICP again, and it got me thinking about
this problem. Initially, my goal was something like: read the book,
work through the exercises, and put the results on GitHub.
&quot;Oh,&quot; I thought, &quot;the code should really have unit
tests written to show that it works. I&#39;ve been wanting to play with
RackUnit anyway&quot;. A few exercises later, I thought, &quot;I should really look into
Scribble for documenting the code I am working on. I could use Plot to
create charts in the Scribble docs, and show interactive examples of
how it all works through the Literate-like facilities in Scribble&quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To be honest, this project definition has grown into something
extremely interesting. I just wish it wasn&#39;t &lt;i&gt;so much work&lt;/i&gt;, a little more
finite, and easier to make progress on. As it stands, this is really a
huge task. I started writing this post because I wanted to debug my
brain, sorting out the threads that compose this phenomenon.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#x2014;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What lessons can I learn? I think I need to be more careful to think
through my project goals, and learn to recognize when I&#39;m changing
them &amp;#x2013; and before changing them, decide if the change is worth the
effort. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/scope-creep/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/scope-creep/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Context</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
I believe &lt;i&gt;context&lt;/i&gt; as a concept is one of the most under-appreciated
ideas in programming. When it is not appreciated and planned for,
context can leak into areas of code that it shouldn&#39;t.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the &quot;Data, Context, and Interaction&quot; (&lt;i&gt;DCI&lt;/i&gt;) model, context takes a
central role. The intuition is that code and ideas may be correct in a
certain context while being confusing and unclear in another.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have an intuitive grasp of what context is. If we talk about a
small piece of code, context might refer to code from the same
package, class, or module. Or, it
might refer to the code&#39;s usage &amp;#x2013; the context from which it is
invoked.
I think this is the most subtle form of coupling due to context that may arise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Occasionally, I encounter code that looks a little strange.
Typically, I&#39;ll then do a search of the code base, trying to find
where that code is called from. Normally, I&#39;m able to understand what
confused me: some oddity in the caller prompted the author to change
the code-in-question, adding some behavior specific to that caller.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
What problems does context leaking cause?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It hampers reuse. I&#39;m less likely to find code useful that has
strange pieces that were specific to some other story from a year
ago. Often, the behavior
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It makes the code more complicated. As I hinted at above, this kind
of thing almost always makes the called code look &lt;i&gt;bizarre&lt;/i&gt;. The
only way to make sense of it being to look up and understand
the context of another caller.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What can be done?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limit context-specific code to &lt;i&gt;that context&lt;/i&gt;. For example, don&#39;t add logic
specific to CSV importing to your core models. If you identify
something that is &lt;i&gt;essential&lt;/i&gt; to the model, sure, add it.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Break your application into modules. When all the concepts in your
application are blended together, it can be really hard to identify
kind of context leakage.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Failure to recognize context and conceptual boundaries will make your
code worse. Throughout my career, it&#39;s something I&#39;ve seen over, and
over, and over again.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/context/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/context/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Backup Your Data, Kids</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
Last weekend, I deleted a directory that was &quot;empty&quot; that included
some of my personal data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use empty with scare quotes because the directory wasn&#39;t actually
empty. I don&#39;t know what exactly caused it, but OS X was listing the
directory as empty. I was trying to figure out what was going on with
something else, noticed the directory, thought it was some junk
directory I never actually used, deleted it, and then a few minutes
later that a &lt;i&gt;number&lt;/i&gt; of directories were mysteriously empty. I
restarted computer and they all came back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I didn&#39;t lose that much data because I do keep most things in
git. However, there were a few projects that I had been working on
recently that I hadn&#39;t pushed remotely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My personal lesson is to not have things that I want to keep not
backed up, no matter how short a time it will be. I know, I know, this
is obvious, common advice, but still.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/backup-your-data-kids/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/backup-your-data-kids/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wish for a New Programming Language</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
There is a principle in program design: defer decisions to the last
possible moment, because this is when you will have the most
information about how to make the right choice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I were to design a new programming language today, I would apply
this to a programming language environment. It would look something
like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A runtime that is small &amp;#x2013; optional, ideally &amp;#x2013; but can grow and be
configured, incorporating ideas from different communities.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A language that is equally small, but growable. This means Lisp,
but I include it from the standpoint of being a reasonable place to
start. Include facilities to extend the actual textual syntax of
the language, not just manipulating sexps.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the more frustrating aspects of programming languages is that
they make tradeoffs up front. The design decisions are made at the
earliest possible moment. These decisions often are as permanent as
the languages themselves are, which is a shame. Programming is a
constantly growing, dynamic field. We will never know less about it
than we know now.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/wish-for-a-new-programming-language/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/wish-for-a-new-programming-language/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I should&#39;a scripted it.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
I was just working on SICP exercise 1.14 and had an interesting
experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The exercise is pretty simple. Draw a tree-graph of the
execution of the ways-to-make-change-counting algorithm from earlier
in the chapter. There is a similar graph of the execution of the
Fibonacci function, so the pieces were all there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead of drawing on paper, I thought, why not create the graph
using a program? That would
certainly make the exercise more interesting.
I&#39;ve been wanting to do something interesting with graphviz, and
drawing the execution tree seemed to be the perfect thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I looked at this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.graphviz.org/pdf/dotguide.pdf&quot;&gt;graphviz tutorial&lt;/a&gt; (warning; PDF) and I
learned how to construct the graph how I wanted pretty quickly. I
spent some time on it, and it worked out well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, if you notice, the SICP exercise specifies drawing the tree for
counting the ways to change 11 cents. In my mind, this seemed like it
should be pretty easy to do &amp;#x2013; it is a very small number, after
all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In actuality, creating this structure was a huge pain.
Editing the nodes, doing calculations, and keeping things in order
ended up taking much longer and was harder than I expectd.
I made mistakes and got confused. Harumph!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wondered, can I somehow &lt;i&gt;script&lt;/i&gt; the creation of this file? Do I
actually need to do this manually? I mean, all I would need to do is
write some strings out to a file&amp;#x2026; it shouldn&#39;t be &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; hard.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I sprinkled some logging-style statements in the code that the
book provides as the definition of the change counting algorithm.
About half an hour later, I had a working, complete graph. Awesome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here&#39;s the complete code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-racket&quot;&gt;#lang racket

(define (gen-count-change-graph)

  (define output-filename &quot;ex1-14.dot&quot;)
  (when (file-exists? output-filename)
      (delete-file output-filename))
  (define output (open-output-file output-filename))
  (define counter 0)
  (define (++counter)
    (let ([ncounter (add1 counter)])
      (set! counter ncounter)
      ncounter))

  (define (record-cc amount kinds-of-coins my-id)
    (fprintf output
	     &quot;\texec~s [label=\&quot;&amp;lt;f0&amp;gt;cc|&amp;lt;f1&amp;gt;~s|&amp;lt;f2&amp;gt;~s\&quot;];\n&quot;
	     my-id amount kinds-of-coins))

  (define (record-1 id parent-id)
    (fprintf output &quot;\toneval~s [label=\&quot;1\&quot;];\n&quot; id)
    (fprintf output &quot;\texec~s -&amp;gt; oneval~s;\n&quot; parent-id id))


  (define (record-0 id parent-id)
    (fprintf output &quot;\tzedval~s [label=\&quot;0\&quot;];\n&quot; id)
    (fprintf output &quot;\texec~s -&amp;gt; zedval~s;\n&quot; parent-id id))

  (define (record-branching left-child-id right-child-id parent-id)
    (fprintf output
	     &quot;\texec~s -&amp;gt; {exec~s; exec~s}\n&quot;
	     parent-id
	     left-child-id
	     right-child-id))

  (define (count-change amount)
    (cc amount 5 counter))

  (define (cc amount kinds-of-coins my-id)
    (record-cc amount kinds-of-coins my-id)
    (let ([left-child-id (++counter)]
	  [right-child-id (++counter)])
      (cond ((= amount 0)
	     (begin
	       (record-1 left-child-id my-id)
	       1))
	    ((or (&amp;lt; amount 0) (= kinds-of-coins 0))
	     (begin
	       (record-0 left-child-id my-id)
	       0))
	     (else (begin
		     (record-branching left-child-id right-child-id my-id)
		     (+ (cc amount
			  (- kinds-of-coins 1)
			  left-child-id)
		      (cc (- amount
			     (first-denomination kinds-of-coins))
			  kinds-of-coins
			  right-child-id)))))))


  (define (first-denomination kinds-of-coins)
    (cond ((= kinds-of-coins 1) 1)
	  ((= kinds-of-coins 2) 5)
	  ((= kinds-of-coins 3) 10)
	  ((= kinds-of-coins 4) 25)
	  ((= kinds-of-coins 5) 50)))

  (display &quot;digraph execution_tree {
node [shape=record];
&quot; output)

  (count-change 11)
  (display &quot; } &quot; output)
  (close-output-port output))

(gen-count-change-graph)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
There were a few interesting facets to this experience:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;org-ol&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The execution graph to count the ways to change 11 cents is
surprisingly large.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The interesting thing is that scripting this solution took
&lt;b&gt;significantly&lt;/b&gt; less time than creating it manually. I probably
spent a few hours of working on this before I ended up starting to
script it, and I was only about half done.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;However, if I hadn&#39;t done it manually for so long, I&#39;m not sure I
would have been able to understand so readily how to generate the
graph &amp;amp; what the dot syntax would be like. For that matter, the
graph I had created manually gave me something to spot-check the
generated graph against. So, I&#39;m not really sure I &lt;i&gt;actually&lt;/i&gt; wasted
time doing it manually.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve heard people say that they might enjoy some movies, but feel
inspired by others. This book really inspires me, which is why I think
I love it so much. The problems are interesting enough that to
&quot;sink my teeth into&quot; them is rewarding in many ways.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/i-shoulda-scripted-it/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/i-shoulda-scripted-it/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Objects Are Like Programs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
Something that has been on my mind for a long time is how similar
objects are to programs, especially Unix programs.
I&#39;m &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.codeclimate.com/blog/2012/11/28/your-objects-the-unix-way/&quot;&gt;not the first&lt;/a&gt; to notice this similarity, but the similarities are
so numerous I find it striking.
Here are a bunch of interesting things, in no particular order:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executables are like classes. They both contain the code necessary
to create new instances: for an executable, that would be a running
program. For a class, that would be an instance.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Programs are best when they are small, focused, and do one thing
well. Similarly, objects are best when they are small and
focused. Is your class more like &lt;i&gt;Microsoft Word&lt;/i&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt;?
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Program reuse comes from this small focus. The same is true of
objects.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Processes conceptually have a lifecycle. They&#39;re &quot;garbage-collected&quot;
by the operating system when they finish executing, just like
objects.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Processes are a combination of code and data, just like
objects. Processes are independent of each other in a similar way to
how instance data is independent between instances.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;There are many ways processes can interact with one another, but the
simplest seem very similar to the way objects should interact: via
sockets. Socket communication is essentially the same as message
passing between objects.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Long-lived objects seem awfully similar to server processes.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the oo-vs-functional debate, I&#39;m somewhere in the middle. I &lt;i&gt;love&lt;/i&gt;
functional programming &amp;#x2013; I just don&#39;t think it is somehow &quot;more
important&quot; than object oriented programming, or that OO is
misguided. Objects are just too general in concept and powerful in
modeling ability. They even model functions rather well, and thus they
can be used rather well for functional programming (when the syntax
allows it; see Ruby).
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/objects-are-like-programs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/objects-are-like-programs/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SICP &amp; Getting the Size of the Current &quot;Stack&quot; in Racket</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve been working through &lt;i&gt;SICP&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;fnr.1&quot; name=&quot;fnr.1&quot; class=&quot;footref&quot; href=&quot;#fn.1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt; again. Its really a great book &amp;#x2013;
and I need to say more about it on here sometime.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am currently on Exercise 1.11, which centers around writing two
separate functions that both compute a mathematical function. The
first function should compute in
a &lt;i&gt;recursive&lt;/i&gt; way and the second should compute in a
&lt;i&gt;iterative&lt;/i&gt; way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The point of writing the function in these different ways is to
highlight the fact that iterative formulations are fast and take
up significantly less memory; in fact, they can be computed
in place/in constant space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I was wrote these, it hit me: It&#39;s interesting to create these
functions, but it would be even more interesting to show that the
computations take up the amount of space we have predicted. So, I set
out to see if I could
figure out how to get current size of the stack, and then to watch the
stack change during the course of both executions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, it doesn&#39;t seem like Racket has the direct concept of
a stack. This doesn&#39;t surprise me, because I understand that the
concept of a stack is a little bit less clear-cut in languages that
support continuations &amp;amp; tail call optimization.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, I was able to find a method &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.racket-lang.org/reference/runtime.html#(def._((quote._~23~25kernel)._vector-set-performance-stats!))&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vector-set-performance-stats!&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
that will provide &quot;the number of bytes currently in use for the
thread&#39;s continuation&quot;. Since a continuation represents the remaining
work that a thread needs to perform as part of its computation, it
seems like this would map fairly directly to the idea of the stack
size showing how each function grows in space during the
computation. If the recursive continuation size
continually grows, and the iterative continuation size stays
constant, that would be strong evidence that this would be answering
my question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Measurements of the stack size performed as predicted. During the
course of the execution, the recursive continuation size kept
growing. Surprisingly, the iterative version kept &lt;b&gt;precisely the
same&lt;/b&gt;. I wasn&#39;t certain at the time that this would be the case, but
to me, this clearly is a success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ok, so how we measure the size of the continuation? The function  &lt;code&gt;get-continuation-size&lt;/code&gt;
below finds the information for us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;org-src-container&quot;&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;src src-scheme&quot;&gt;(define (get-continuation-size)
  (let ((results (make-vector 20)))
    (vector-set-performance-stats! results (current-thread))
    ;; item 3 contains continuation size
    (vector-ref results 3)))
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m going to keep using this code to show exactly the same thing &amp;#x2013;
that functions are executing within the space we expect them to.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;text-footnotes&quot;&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footdef&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;fn.1&quot; name=&quot;fn.1&quot; class=&quot;footnum&quot; href=&quot;#fnr.1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class=&quot;footpara&quot;&gt;
: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book.html&quot;&gt;http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/get-current-stack-size-in-racket/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/get-current-stack-size-in-racket/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Automated Workstation Setup &amp; Management</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, I have written lots of scripts to help automate
something or other. Many of these have broken. Example of the scripts
that have broken include a
LastPass data exporter and encrypter in Ruby, Emacs Lisp of various
kinds that integrate Emacs with other
processes, a tiny script to toggle my Heroku authentication between
my personal and work accounts, and others. Typically, I find
this out about their brokenness at the worst possible time &amp;#x2013; when I
need to actually use the scripts I rely upon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This has become common enough that I have grown to expect it. Lots of
things might cause one of these scripts to break: software upgrades,
making incompatible changes to other pieces of code, accidentally
removing something that the script relied upon have all played a part
in things breaking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I really hate this. Taking the time to write something, only to have
it be broken when you need it, makes you feel like you wasted your
time writing the scripts in the first place. Because of this
phenomenon, I tend to write fewer scripts and be more accepting of
discomfort.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I really hate this, too. I believe we &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; script things. I believe
this is a &lt;i&gt;key&lt;/i&gt; to being a productive programmer, and is one way that
allows us to multiply out abilities as programmers.
And, I&#39;m not alone in
thinking this way. It seems that all the best developers think the
same thing: laziness is a virtue. Script away the things you would
otherwise have to do manually.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;ve come to believe that an automated setup &amp;amp; configuration
management system is the key for me to solve these problems. If I could
safely reproduce the environment wherein my software works, and I
had tests around the software, then I could write scripts more
effectively and with greater freedom. I would be able to get back some
of the effectiveness I am missing out on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the past year or so I have been making a concerted effort to
solve this problem. Some things have worked out really well, others
have not. At some point, the software to build this site was broken,
and I didn&#39;t know why, and out of frustration I stopped writing and
focused intensely on setting things up correctly from first
principles. I&#39;m nowhere near done, but it is time to start talking
about what I have discovered.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/automated-workstation-setup-and-management/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/automated-workstation-setup-and-management/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Literate Programming Primer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;
I love the concept of literate programming. Unfortunately, the
idea never really caught on in industry. My experiments with it in
the past have been successful, but there are many things
that could be done to improve the experience &amp;#x2013; many of which
prevent me from advocating it to other programmers to practice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Literate programming is a technique invented by Don Knuth many years
ago. Essentially, the idea is to embed code inside of an expository
document that describes the code.
That code makes up the program, and the surrounding documents provide
insight into how and why the code does what it does.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have only personally used the LP facilities provided by &lt;a href=&quot;http://orgmode.org/&quot;&gt;Org&lt;/a&gt;
(which are rather good), but I have read Knuth&#39;s paper that introduces
LP, and have that familiarity with it. I mention this because there
may be &quot;prior art&quot; that is relevant to some of what I say that I am
unaware of.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A basic LP system lets an author define blocks of code in a
document. These blocks may be associated with a file: when the
&quot;tangle&quot; process occurs, these blocks are written to that associated
file. Thus, the content in the document can may then be executed, etc
in a traditional manner.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Blocks may be named. A block of code may reference another block by
it&#39;s name. When &quot;file&quot; blocks are written to disk, any name-references they
contain are replaced by the contents of the blocks they reference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, here are some ideas I would like to see explored:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;org-ul&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Wiki as an organizational model. Most (all?) LP systems favor a
highly hierarchical document organization, such as a white
paper. This works for well-defined programs that will not change
over time.

&lt;p&gt;
However, I have never seen a living, active project that has that
kind of structure. To me, a &quot;Wiki&quot; feels much more appropriate for
how an actual project grows.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;How does literate programming influence the design of code? I fear
that the structure provided by a LP document may mean that code
itself is poorly structured.

&lt;p&gt;
I know from personal experience that, looking at a LP document, it
is harder to see the underlying code structure
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;One pain point I have felt is that any file that needs to be
commented on in a literate document &lt;i&gt;also&lt;/i&gt; needs to be maintained by
that document in its entirety. So, for example, in order to make a
change to a file that was generated externally requires the
inclusion of the entire file inside the document.

&lt;p&gt;
However, if literate programming documents had first class support
for diffs of files not handled in the current system, this problem
would go away. Of course, editing diffs by hand is hard, and so some
deeper thought about diff-generation needs to be applied.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;What is the relationship between literate programming and other
forms of code commentary, such as code comments, commit messages,
and pull request discussions?

&lt;p&gt;
I certainly don&#39;t know the answer to this one, but it is an
interesting question. Most developers (myself included,
interestingly) tend to dislike code comments. However, literate
programming feels very different 
from adding comments to code, although from a superficial
examination they seem very similar. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And, although code comments are frowned upon, many developers have
strong opinions about commit messages &amp;#x2013; and isn&#39;t a commit message
very similar to a code comment?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Git makes it easy to dig up information in commit
messages. Accessing the comments from GitHub pull requests is much
less easy, though. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&#39;m looking into this now for practical reasons: I am working on a
literate document, but feel torn: I want to write the document for the
basis of something I will be using in the future, but also making it
publishable. For now, I&#39;ll just plug away, because I need to publish.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/literate-programming-primer/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://joelmccracken.github.io//entries/literate-programming-primer/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
